Great creativity. In times of need, we need great creativity.
الإبداع الجيد، في بعض الأوقات، نحتاج إليه
Discuss. Great creativity is astonishingly, absurdly, rationally, irrationally powerful.
ناقش. الإبداع الجيد مذهل وسخيف ومنطقي، وغير منطقي في تأثيره
Great creativity can spread tolerance, champion freedom,
يمكن للإبداع الجيد أن ينشر التسامح والحرية
make education seem like a bright idea.
وأن يجعل التعليم يبدو وكأنه فكرة براقة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Great creativity can turn a spotlight on deprivation,
الإبداع الجيد يمكنه أن يسلط الضوء على الحرمان
or show that deprivation ain't necessarily so.
أو يجعله بلا فائدة
Great creativity can make politicians electable,
الإبداع الجيد يمكن أن يجعل السياسيين منتخبين،
or parties unelectable.
أو الأحزاب غير مرغوب فيها
It can make war seem like tragedy or farce.
يمكنه أن يجعل الحرب تبدو وكأنها مأساة.. أو مسرحية هزلية
Creativity is the meme-maker that puts slogans on our t-shirts
الإبداع مثل القلم الذي يكتب الشعارات على قمصاننا
and phrases on our lips.
أو العبارات على شفاهنا
It's the pathfinder that shows us a simple road
إنه المستكشف الذي يرينا الطريق البسيط
through an impenetrable moral maze.
عبر المتاهة الروحية المبهمة
Science is clever, but great creativity is something less knowable,
العلم ذكي, ولكن الإبداع الجيد هو شيء أقل انتشارا،
more magical. And now we need that magic.
وأكثر سحرا.. وهذا ما نحتاج إليه الآن
This is a time of need.
هذا هو وقت الحاجة إليه
Our climate is changing quickly, too quickly.
مناخنا يتغير بشكل سريع, سريع جدا.
And great creativity is needed to do what it does so well:
و الإبداع الجيد مطلوب حتى يقوم بما هو مؤهل له:
to provoke us to think differently with dramatic creative statements.
الحث على التفكير بشكل مختلف مع العنواين الإبداعية الدرامية
To tempt us to act differently
الإغراء على التصرف بشكل مختلف
with delightful creative scraps.
مع لمسات إبداعية مبهجة
Here is one such scrap from an initiative I'm involved in
هذه إحداها، مبادرة مني
using creativity to inspire people to be greener.
استخدمت الابداع لتحفيز الناس ليكونوا أصدقاء للبيئة
(Video) Man: You know, rather than drive today, I'm going to walk.
فيديو: الرجل: أنت تعلم، بدل من قيادة السيارة اليوم، سأقوم بالمشي
Narrator: And so he walked, and as he walked he saw things.
الراوي : ومشى، أثناء ذلك رأى أشياء
Strange and wonderful things he would not otherwise have seen.
أشياء غريبة ورائعة لم يكن ليرها..
A deer with an itchy leg. A flying motorcycle.
ظبي كسرت ساقه.. دراجة نارية تطير..
A father and daughter separated from a bicycle by a mysterious wall.
أب وابنته يفصلهما عن الدراجة جدار غريب..
And then he stopped. Walking in front of him was her.
ثم توقف.. حينما مرت هي من أمامه..
The woman who as a child had skipped with him through fields
المرأة التي عرجت معه إلى الحقول وهي صغيرة
and broken his heart.
وكسر قلبها..
Sure, she had aged a little.
بالتأكيد، لقد كبرت قليلاً..
In fact, she had aged a lot.
في الواقع، لقد كبرت كثيراً..
But he felt all his old passion for her return.
لكنه شعر بكل طموحه القديم لعودتها..
"Ford," he called softly. For that was her name.
"فورد"، ناداها بلطف، كان ذلك هو اسمها
"Don't say another word, Gusty," she said,
قالت، "لا تقل كلمة أخرى، جيستي.."
for that was his name.
ذاك كان اسمه..
"I know a tent next to a caravan, exactly 300 yards from here.
أعرف خيمة بجوار المخيم، تبعد 300 ياردة من هنا
Let's go there and make love. In the tent."
لنذهب هناك ونمارس الحب..
Ford undressed. She spread one leg, and then the other.
تهيأت فورد له
Gusty entered her boldly and made love to her rhythmically
وضمها جستي إليه
while she filmed him, because she was a keen amateur pornographer.
بينما صورته هي، لأنها كانت تهوى التصوير
The earth moved for both of them.
تمايلت الأرض لهما
And they lived together happily ever after.
وعاشوا معا، سعداء للأبد
And all because he decided to walk that day.
كل ذلك لأنه قرر أن يمشي في ذلك اليوم..
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Andy Hobsbawm: We've got the science, we've had the debate.
أندي هوبسباوم : لدينا العلم، وكان لدينا نقاش
The moral imperative is on the table.
الأمر الأخلاقي الإلزامي مطروح على الطاولة
Great creativity is needed to take it all,
الإبداع الجيد مطلوب
make it simple and sharp.
لنجعله بسيطا وقاطعا
To make it connect. To make it make people want to act.
حتى يصل إلى الناس.. حتى يحثهم على الفعل
So this is a call, a plea,
هذا نداء، ورجاء
to the incredibly talented TED community.
إلى مجتمع تيد الموهوب
Let's get creative against climate change.
لنوظف الإبداع ضد تغير المناخ
And let's do it soon. Thank you.
ولنقم به عاجلا.. شكرا لكم!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)